A Guide to the Richmond YWCA records, 1901-2002
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Richmond YWCA records 1901-2002
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 373
16 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department on March 6, 2004.
Historical Information
The YWCA (Young Women's Christian Association) is a movement made up of numerous local, national, and international organizations. These organizations seek to support and empower women, families, and communities by promoting peace and social justice. Launched in 1855 in England by a group of women concerned about the physical and spiritual welfare of young women leaving their homes in rural areas to find work in industrializing cities, the YWCA movement quickly spread to countries around the world, including the United States, where the first YWCA was organized in New York City in 1858. Over time, the work of YWCA organizations has expanded to include services, programs, and advocacy activities in the areas of fitness, women's health, employment, education, poverty, civil rights, and domestic violence.
The YWCA of Richmond was founded in 1887 as the Women's Christian Association of Richmond by a group of Richmond women who wanted to assist young women traveling to the city to work. In 1888, the group opened its first boarding house, and in 1890, established a nursery and kindergarten, Richmond's first, for the children of women working in Richmond's factories. The women staying at the boarding house were provided with access to medical care, an extensive library, sewing classes, and prayer groups. As YWCAs sprung up across the country, interest grew in promoting cooperation at the national level, and in 1907, the Richmond YWCA became a charter member of the national YWCA, later known as YWCA USA.
Membership in the YWCA of Richmond grew rapidly, and as it did, the organization was able to expand its services and programs. In 1910, the organization opened a gymnasium where young women could exercise to promote good health and relieve stress. Other programs established in the 1910s included employment referrals, meal services, sex education, English lessons, job and domestic science training, and social clubs.
With segregation firmly entrenched in Richmond, as in much of the South, the YWCA founded in 1887 only permitted white membership and provided services exclusively to white clients. However, from an early date there was strong interest, particularly among members of the African American community, in establishing a YWCA organization in Richmond to assist young, African American women and their children. In 1912, this goal was achieve when a group of over 200 Richmond women were granted a charter for the Phyllis Wheatley Branch of the YWCA of Richmond.
Over the course of the following decades, the YWCA organizations of Richmond continued to expand their services. This expansion included the addition of Girl Reserves programs, later known as Y-Teens, as well as day camps and additional recreational and exercise programing.
Efforts to bring the segregated YWCA units together began early on, but moved forward gradually. In 1925, a member of the Phyllis Wheatly Branch's management committee joined the Richmond YWCA's board of directors, and in 1930, both YWCA organizations played an active role in the creation of the Southern Commission on Interracial Cooperation. During the 1960s, all programing became fully integrated. The national YWCA identified civil rights as a priority during this time, and at its 1970 annual convention, the national YWCA announced its commitment to eliminating racism, a goal which has remained a key component of the national YWCA and the Richmond YWCA's objectives.
In addition increasing its focus on issues surrounding racism and civil rights at this time, the Richmond YWCA also began to offer more programs and services addressing sexual assault and domestic violence. The organization was one of the first in the Richmond area to establish a sexual assault center and a women's shelter, both opened in 1979. The organization also maintained its dedication to serving children during this time, establishing a preschool program of homeless children in 1989.
In 1996, the Richmond YWCA ceased to provide health and fitness services, choosing instead to focus exclusively on programs addressing domestic violence, sexual violence, and early childhood education. As of 2016, the Richmond YWCA staffed a 24 hour domestic and sexual violence hotline, provided counseling and emergency housing for survivors of domestic and sexual violence, operated an accredited preschool, and offered a variety of programs aimed at empowering women of all ages in the Greater Richmond community.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of records created or acquired by the YWCA of Richmond in the course of its regular operations. Materials found in the collection include reports, minutes, budgets, financial records, correspondence, lists, memoranda, bylaws, attendance records, manuals, schedules, proposals, deeds, printed materials, and photographic materials dating from 1901 to 2002.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into eleven series: Series 1: Board Committees and Records, 1946-2000; Series 2: Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes and Records, 1964-1998; Series 3: Facility, Infrastructure, and Renovation Records, 1978-2001; Series 4: Financial Records and Materials, 1917-1975; Series 5: Other Financial Records, 1905-2001; Series 6: Other Financial Records - Richmond Community Fund, 1925-1949; Series 7: Papers on YWCA Properties, 1907-1986; Series 8: Staff, 1971-1992; Series 9: Other Organizational Records and Materials, 1901-2002; Series 10: Certificate, Comic, Manuals, Photographs, and Proclamations, 1931-2001; and Series 11: Architectural Drawings, Floor Plans and Site Plans, 1963-2000.
Files in series 1, series 2, and series 4 are arranged chronologially. Files in series 3, series 5, series 7, series 10, and series 11 are arranged alphabetically. Files in series 6 are grouped by type and arranged thereunder alphabetically or chronologically. Files in series 8 are arranged alphabetically by folder heading, there under chronologically. Files in Series 9 are arranged alphabetically by folder heading, and folders in the file unit "organizational materials" are arranged thereunder alpha-numerically by file code.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
The following items have been separated from the collection and individually catalogued. They are held in the Special Collections and Archives Department.
Boyd, Nancy. Emissaries, the Overseas work of the American YWCA 1895-1970. 1986.
Hatcher, O. Latham, Ph. D., ed. Occupations for Women: A Study made for the Southern Women's Educational Alliance. 1927.
National Board Young Women's Christian Associations. Proceedings of the Fifteenth National Convention of the Young Women's Christian Association of the United States of America. Columbus, Ohio - April 22-28, 1938. Section I Business of the Convention.
Quayle, Margaret S. As Told By Business Girls, Problems in Personal Adjustment. 1932.
Rice, Anna V. A History of the World's Young Women's Christian Association. 1947.
Sims, Mary S. The Natural History of a Social Institution - The YWCA. 1936. (2 Copies)
Contents List
- Series 1: Board Committees and Records, 1946-2000
  - Finance Committee, 1946 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1968 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Camp, Christian Life, Finance, Program Staff, Miscellaneous Materials, Richmond International Council and Membership, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Rosters, Personnel Policies, Board of Directors Minutes, HPER(Health, Physical Education and Recreation), Adult Activities, Youth Services, Public Affairs, World Fellowship and Committee on Administration, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1970 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1971 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1972 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1973 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1974 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1975 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1976 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - YWCA Board Committees List, YWCA Board of Directors, YWCA Committee Job Descriptions, Action Audit, Ad Hoc Lumsden, Ad Hoc Parking, Adult, Building, Convention, Executive, Finance, HPER (Health, Physical Education and Recreation) and Membership, 1979 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Planning and Priorities, Public Affairs, Public Relations, World Mutual Service, and Youth Committee, 1979 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - YWCA Board of Directors, YWCA Board Committees, YWCA Board of Directors - All Female, Non-board Committee Members, Action Audit, Building and Grounds and Building Renovation, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Chamberlayne Building Sale, Child Care, Executive, Finance, HPER (Health, Physical Education and Recreation), Association Nominating and Task Force on Nontraditional Occupations, 1980 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Personnel, Program Development, Public Affairs, Public Relations/Membership/Annual Meeting, Teen, and Victim Advocacy Program, 1980 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Volunteer Leadership and World Mutual Service, 1980 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Officers, Committees' List, Committee Job Descriptions, Non-board Committee Members, Action Audit, Association Nominating Committee, Building and Grounds, Child Development and Executive Committee, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Finance, HPER (Health, Physical Education and Recreation), Personnel, Policies and Procedures, Program Development, Public Affairs, Public Relations/Annual Meeting/ Membership and Victim Advocacy Program, 1981 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Shelter Committee, Volunteer Leadership, Women's Community Network and World Mutual Service, 1981 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Board of Directors, Bylaws, Board Officers' List, Board Committees' List, Committee Job Descriptions, Meeting Dates, Executive, Finance, Financial Development, Investment Advisory, Membership, and Association Nominating Committee, 1982 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Personnel, Program Development, HPER (Health, Physical Education and Recreation), Public Affairs, Outstanding Women's Dinner (Subcommittee of Public Relations), Women's Community Network and World Mutual Service, 1982 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - YWCA Board of Directors' List, Calendar, Committees' List, Bylaws and Bylaws Committee, Annual Awards Luncheon/ OWGRA, Building and Grounds, Executive and Finance Committee, 1983 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Financial Development, Membership, Association Nominating Committee, Board Nominating Committee and Personnel, 1983 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Program, Public Affairs, Public Relations, Women's Community Network, and World Mutual Service, 1983 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Board of Directors' List, Committees' List, Association Review, Awards Luncheon, Children's Center, and Executive Committee, 1984 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Finance Committee, 1984 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Financial Development, Health and Fitness/ HPER (Health, Physical Education and Recreation), Leadership Tea, Membership, Personnel, Public Affairs, Public Relations, VAP, World Mutual Service, Young Women's Center, Association Nominating Committee, Board Nominating Committee and Library Refurnishing Committee, 1984 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Association Nominating Committee, Calendar, Board Committee List, Awards Luncheon and Executive Committee, 1985 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Finance, Finance Development, Health and Fitness, Personnel, Public Affairs, Public Relations, Women's Advocacy and World Mutual Service, 1985 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - YWCA Board Committees' List, Executive and Finance, 1986 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Financial Development, Health and Fitness, Law, Marketing, Membership, Personnel, Public Affairs, Women's Advocacy Program, Women's History Week, World Mutual Service, Youth and Outstanding Women's Awards, 1986 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Board of Directors, Board Committees, Annual Meeting Committee, Association Nominating Committee, Executive Committee and Finance Committee, 1987 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Financial Development, Health and Fitness, Law, Long-Range Planning and Marketing Committee, 1987 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Board Committees - Membership, Outstanding Women Awards, Personnel, Public Affairs, Women's Advocacy Program, Women's History Week, World Mutual Service and Youth, 1987 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Annual Meeting, Association Nominating Committee, Board Meeting Materials, Board Nominating Committee and Executive Committee, 1988 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Finance Committee, 1988 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Board Committees - Financial Development, Health and Fitness, Long-Range Strategic Planning Committee, Marketing, Outstanding Women Awards, Personnel, Public Affairs, 1988 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Silent Auction, Women's Advocacy, World Mutual Service, Youth and Search Committee, 1988 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Annual Meeting, Association Nominating Committee and Board Meeting Materials, 1989 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Board Nominating Committee, Building and Grounds, Executive Committee, 1989 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Finance Committee, 1989 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Financial Development and Long-Range Planning Committee, 1989 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Marketing, Outstanding Women Awards, Personnel, Silent Auction, Women's Advocacy Program, World Mutual Service, Child Care and Teen Committee, 1989 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Calendar, Annual Meeting, Board Meeting and Materials, Board Miscellaneous, Building and Grounds and Child Care Committee, January-June, 1990 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Executive Committee, January-June, 1990 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Finance Committee, January-June, 1990 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Board Committees - Financial Plan, Financial Development, Health and Fitness, Long-Range Planning, Membership, Outstanding Women Awards, Personnel, Teens, Women's Advocacy Program and World Mutual Service, January-June, 1990 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Board Committees - Association Nominating Committee, Board Meeting and Materials, Board Miscellaneous, Building and Grounds, Child Care and Development Committee, July-December, 1990 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Executive Committee, July-December, 1990 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Finance Committee, July-December, 1990 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Health and Fitness, Long-Range Strategic Planning, Outstanding Women's Awards, Marketing, Personnel, Teen, Women's Advocacy Program and World Mutual Service, July-December, 1990 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Annual Meeting, Association Nominating Committee, Board Minutes and Materials, Board Miscellaneous, Building and Grounds, Child Care and Development, January-June, 1991 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Executive and Finance Committee, January-June, 1991 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Health and Fitness, Long-Range Strategic Planning, Outstanding Women Awards, Personnel, Teen and World Mutual Service, January-June, 1991 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Board Meeting and Materials and Board Miscellaneous, July-December, 1991 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Board Resources, Building and Grounds, Development and Executive, July-December, 1991 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Finance, Long-Range Planning, Personnel, Program and World Mutual Service, July-December, 1991 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Board Meeting and Materials, Board Miscellaneous, Board Nominating Committee and Building and Grounds, 1992 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Development, Executive, Finance and Long-Range Plans Committee, 1992 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Marketing, Personnel, Program and World Mutual Service Committee, 1992 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, February-June, 1993 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, July-December, 1993 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Board Committees - Finance Committee Minutes, January-June, 1994 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, July-December, 1994 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, January-June, 1995 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, August-December, 1995 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Nominating Committee Materials and Records, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, February-June, 1996 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, July-December, 1996 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, January-June, 1997 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, July-December 1997 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, January-May, 1998 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Finance Task Force - Memos and Minutes, August-December, 1998 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Nominating Task Force, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Finance Task Force - Memos and Minutes, January-May, 1999 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Finance Task Force - Calendar, Memos and Minutes, July-December, 1999 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Finance Task Force - Calendar, Memos and Minutes, February-April, 2000 (Box-folder 4:17)
- Series 2: Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes and Records, 1964-1998
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record and Minutes, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Board of Directors - YWCA Board of Directors' Lists, Minutes and Materials, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Board of Directors - Board of Directors' List, Bylaws, Minutes and Materials, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Board of Directors' List, Minutes and Materials, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Board of Directors' List, Attendance Record and Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Board of Directors - YWCA Board of Directors' List, Attendance Record, and Minutes, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Board of Directors - YWCA Board of Directors' List, Attendance Record, and Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, Reports and Materials, 1976 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Board of Directors - Minutes and Materials, 1977 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Board of Directors - Minutes, 1978 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, 1979 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes and Materials, 1980 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Board of Directors - Board of Directors' List, Board Committees and Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, August-December, 1981 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-September, 1982 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, October-December, 1982 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Board of Directors - Minutes and Materials, January-December, 1983 (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - YWCA Board of Directors' List, Minutes and Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Board of Directors - Materials including Board of Directors' List, Committee List, Committee Job Descriptions, Bylaws, Policies, Affirmative Action Plan and Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record, Schedule and Minutes, January-December, 1985 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record, Schedule, Board of Directors' List and Minutes, 1986 (Box-folder 5:21)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, Meeting Schedule, Calendar, Attendance Record and Board Member List, January-November, 1987 (Box-folder 5:22)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes and Attendance Record, January-November, 1988 (Box-folder 5:23)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record and Minutes, January-December, 1989 (Box-folder 5:24)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record, Calendar and Minutes, January-June, 1990 (Box-folder 5:25)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, July-December, 1990 (Box-folder 5:26)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record and Minutes, 1991 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record, Calendar and Minutes, 1992 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-June, 1993 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, July-December, 1993 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-June, 1994 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record and Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-June, 1995 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Attendance Record and Minutes, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-May, 1996 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, July-December, 1996 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-June, 1997 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, July-December, 1997 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee - Minutes, January-June, 1998 (Box-folder 6:13)
- Series 3: Facility, Infrastructure, and Renovation Records, 1978-2001
  - Facility - A Building Manual for the YWCA, 1978 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Facility - Market Search for YWCA, undated (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Infrastructure - Computer and Phones, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Infrastructure - Halifax Corporation - Wide Area Network Citrix Metaframe / Windows 2000 Infrastructure for YWCA, 2001 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Infrastructure - Halifax Corporation - Wide Area Network Windows 2000 Infrastructure for YWCA, 2001 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Infrastructure - PSINet - Proposal for YWCA Celie Center Prepared by Greg Kidd, 2001 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Renovation - Account Bank Statements, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Renovation - Account Invoices, 1981 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Renovation - Architect's Agreement - Bond, Comet, Westmoreland, and Hiner Architects Inc., 1998-2001 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Renovation - Asbestos Bids, 2000 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Renovation - Asbestos Containing Materials and Lead Based Paint Survey Report for YWCA, 1998 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Renovation - Bond, Comet, Westmoreland, and Hiner - Interview Presentation for Renovation of YWCA Facility Child Care Center HVAC Systems and General Office Space, 1998 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - Renovation - Bond, Hugo and Farley Correspondence, 2001 (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Renovation - Building Committee - Capital Campaign, 1998, 2000, undated (Box-folder 7:14)
  - Renovation - Childcare Furniture / Equipment List, 2000 (Box-folder 7:15)
  - Renovation - Code Modification Request, 2000 (Box-folder 7:16)
  - Renovation - Construction Budget, 2000, undated (Box-folder 7:17)
  - Renovation - Construction Group Minutes, 2000 (Box-folder 7:18)
  - Renovation - Construction Schedule, 2001 (Box-folder 7:19)
  - Renovation - Correspondence on the Installation of Donor Wall Marble Plaque and Pool Fence, 2001 (Box-folder 7:20)
  - Renovation - Correspondence, Receipts and Records, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 7:21)
  - Renovation - Correspondence and Records, 2000 (Box-folder 7:22)
  - Renovation - Donors and Contributions, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 7:23)
  - Renovation - Fire and Sprinkler, 2000 (Box-folder 7:24)
  - Renovation - Furniture, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 7:25)
  - Renovation - Historic Tax Credit - Correspondence and Records, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 7:26)
  - Renovation - HPER Pool Renovations - Correspondence, Receipts, and Records, 1982 (Box-folder 7:27)
  - Renovation - HPER Renovation Plan, Glave, Newman and Anderson Packet, and Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 7:28)